Finding Aid for Section of Thoracic Surgery (University of Michigan) records, 1927-1960.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Section of Thoracic Surgery (University of Michigan) records 1927-1960
University of Michigan. Section of Thoracic Surgery.
20 linear feet
9665 Bimu 2
A division of the Department of Surgery of the University of Michigan Hospital, established the nation's first residency training program in thoracic surgery in 1928; documents development of the program at Michigan and advances in surgical procedures, includes correspondence, operation notes, case studies, and photographs and negatives of patients and surgical procedures.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Accession No. 8401 ) was received in September 1995 through Dr. Herbert Sloan.
The record group University of Michigan Section of Thoracic Surgery contains restricted patient records; these files are interspersed throughout the entire record group. Because of the existence of patient information, access to the entire record group (with the exception of published articles and photographs) is governed by the patient record access restriction policies explained below. Consult the Bentley Library for procedures for gaining access to the records.
The University of Michigan Section of Thoracic Surgery was an outgrowth of the growing specialization within the field of surgery which occurred after 1900. Rapid advances in surgical knowledge and techniques led to the development of surgical sub-specialties. Although operations on the chest such as the drainage of empyema and lung abscesses had occasionally been performed in the University Hospital, it wasn't until 1920 that thoracic surgery began to emerge as a specialty at the University of Michigan.
In 1920, John Alexander came to the University of Michigan at the invitation of Dr. Hugh Cabot and was given the assignment of developing a clinic in thoracic surgery. Alexander quickly established the University of Michigan as a major center for the study and practice of thoracic surgery, and the publication of his book The Surgery of Pulmonary Tuberculosis, in 1925 was considered a landmark and did much to stimulate interest on the subject. Shortly before the publication of his book Alexander contracted tuberculosis, a condition that although arrested, would continue to plague him.
In 1927, the first thoracoplasty for tuberculosis in Michigan was performed at the University Hospital, and soon after Alexander limited his work entirely to thoracic surgery. In 1928 Alexander established the nation's first residency training program in thoracic surgery. Although tuberculosis was on the decline, it remained a formidable disease and was the major focus of thoracic surgery. In 1928 there were over 3,000 deaths from tuberculosis in Michigan. An arrangement was worked with the Michigan State Sanatorium at Howell in which the thoracic surgery staff members became consultants to the sanatorium. Two floors were added to the University Hospital in 1930 and 1931 for the care of patients with pulmonary tuberculosis. The number of patients referred to the university for surgical treatment of diseases of the chest continued to grow steadily such that by 1931 it was necessary to add to the thoracic surgery staff.
Cameron Haight joined the staff in 1931, and the following year the university instituted the first two-year training program in thoracic surgery. Haight became a leading surgeon in thoracic surgical techniques, and performed the first pneumonectomy in the Western Hemisphere and the second in the world. The University of Michigan played a major role in the development of thoracic surgery as it came of age as a specialty during World War II. Following the war, the discovery of effective anti-tuberculosis drugs reduced the need for the resection of pulmonary tissue. Gradually the sanatoriums emptied and new developments in thoracic surgery replaced the many operations for tuberculosis.
In 1954 Alexander died and was succeeded by Haight as head of thoracic surgery. The first open heart operation at the University of Michigan was performed in 1956 and soon cardiac surgery became the most important part of the section's activity. Michigan quickly became one of the major centers in the country for the surgical treatment of heart disease, particularly congenital heart disease. With cardiac surgery firmly established, members of the section turned their attention to heart and lung transplantation and in 1968, Edward Kahn performed the first of several successful heart transplants.
Haight died in 1970 and was succeeded by Herbert Sloan as head of the Section of Thoracic Surgery. The section developed specialties for the surgical treatment of diseases of the esophagus and conducted ongoing research in heart and lung transplantation, cardiac valve homografts, and myocardial preservation. In 1984 Mark Orringer replaced Sloan as head of the Section of Thoracic Surgery. The clinical services continued to grow. In 1990 the Section performed a total of 1709 thoracic surgical operations, and from 1984 to 1990 the Section performed 173 heart transplants. The section continues to maintain a position of national and international leadership in the field of thoracic surgery.
For further information regarding the development of the Section of Thoracic Surgery at the University of Michigan, researchers are advised to consult Horace Davenport's book, University of Michigan Surgeons 1850-1970 Who They Were and What They Did. (Ann Arbor, MI: Historical Center for the Health Sciences, University of Michigan, 1993).
The records of the Section of Thoracic Surgery document the growth and development of thoracic surgery at the University of Michigan from its origins as a clinic to its emergence as a specialized section within the Department of Surgery. The records, covering the period from 1927 to 1960, are comprised of correspondence, operation notes, case studies, and photographs and negatives of patients and surgical procedures. Together, these materials richly illustrate the development of thoracic surgery techniques during the 1930s and 1940s.
Because patient names appear throughout the record group as well as in the photographs and negatives, patient privacy is a major concern and researchers must comply with the access restrictions described elsewhere in this finding aid.
The record group is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1927-1960 (16 linear ft.)
Operative Notes, 1927-1954 (2.8 linear ft.)
Papers and Notes, 1929-1949 (0.2 linear ft.)
Photographs and Negatives, 1929-1957 (1 linear ft.)
Form and Genre:
Photographs.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Section of Thoracic Surgery.; Chest--Surgery.; Thoracic surgeons.; Tuberculosis.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Michigan Tuberculosis Association.; Alexander, John, 1891-; American Trudeau Society.; Haight, Cameron.; Tuberculosis--Hospitals--Michigan--Howell.
Contributors:
Bethune, Norman.; Blalock, Alfred, 1899-1964.; Coller, Frederick A.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939.; Cutler, Elliott Carr, 1888-1947.; Frazier, Charles H. (Charles Harrison), 1870-1936.; Graham, Evarts A. (Evarts Ambrose), 1883-1957; Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1886-; Nissen, Rudolf, 1896-; Sauerbruch, Ferdinand, 1875-1951.; Sloan, Herbert.; Sergent, Emile, 1867-1943.; Steele, John Dutton.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan. Section of Thoracic Surgery.; Tuberculosis.; Surgery.; Bronchoscopy.; Empyema.; Pneumonectomy.; Lungs--Abscess.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; Haight, Cameron.; Alexander, John, 1891-; University of Michigan. Medical School. Class of 1943.; Photographs.
- Correspondence 1927-1960, 16 linear feet
  The Correspondence series comprises the bulk of the documentation. The records consist of both incoming and outgoing correspondence and include discussions of thoracic cases, patient referrals, case histories, as well as information on former students and residents, and professional material relating to presentations, articles, and various surgical and medical organizations. The creation of the first two-year training program in thoracic surgery is particularly well documented. The correspondence was primarily sent or received by John Alexander and Cameron Haight although other surgeons within the Section of Thoracic Surgery are also represented.
  The correspondence deals extensively with tuberculosis and includes letters and reports from sanatoriums and physicians throughout Michigan and the world. Alexander, who himself suffered from tuberculosis, wrote extensively on the topic as evidenced in these records. Correspondents include numerous pioneers and luminaries in the field of thoracic surgery and illustrates the growing specialization within the field. Key correspondents include: Alfred Blalock; Norman Bethune; Duane Carr; Frederick Coller; Harvey Cushing; Elliott Cutler; Evarts Graham; Samuel C. Harvey; Charles H. Frazier; Rudolf Nissen; Ferdinand Sauerbruch; Emile Sergent; Robert Shaw; and John D. Steele.
  The correspondence has been retained in its original order. Correspondence is filed by year and alphabetically within each year, although the individual letters are not alphabetized within folders. The alphabetical arrangement is a mixture of filing by the name of the sender and topical filing by the person or subject of the letter. For example, letters from Evarts Graham will be found under "G" for Graham as well as under "J" when the subject was the Journal of Thoracic Surgery. There are several gaps within this series, and in some instances a portion of the alphabet is missing for particular years. The filing is generally only by letter, A-Z, although specific subjects begin to appear in the later years such as " American Review of Tuberculosis," " Tuberculosis Sanatorium Commission," " postgraduates," and " veterans administration." From 1955 to 1958 a more topical arrangement is present.
  - 1927-1929
    - A-Z, 22 folders (Box 1)
      [Restricted, Patient Records]
  - 1930
    - A-Z, 22 folders (Box 1)
  - 1931
    - A-Z, 22 folders (Box 1)
  - 1932
    - A-Z, 27 folders (Box 2)
  - 1933
    - A-M, 14 folders (Box 2)
    - N-Z, 11 folders (Box 3)
  - 1934
    - J-Z, 17 folders (Box 3)
  - 1935
    - A-G, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - H-Z, 22 folders (Box 4)
  - 1936
    - A-L, 15 folders (Box 4)
    - M-Z, 13 folders (Box 5)
  - 1937
    - A-R, 23 folders (Box 5)
    - S-Z, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - 1938
    - A-S, 22 folders (Box 6)
  - 1939
    - A-E, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - N-S, 7 folders (Box 7)
  - 1940
    - A-E, N-S, 13 folders (Box 7)
  - 1941
    - A-L, 13 folders (Box 7)
    - M (Box 8)
    - Michigan Tuberculosis Association, 1937-1941, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - N-Z, 13 folders (Box 8)
  - 1942
    - A-O, 18 folders (Box 8)
    - P-Z, 12 folders (Box 9)
  - 1943
    - A-W, 24 folders (Box 9)
  - 1944 (Box 10)
    - A-W, 23 folders (Box 10)
  - 1945
    - A-P, 20 folders (Box 10)
    - R-Z, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - 1946
    - A-P, 21 folders (Box 11)
    - R-Z, 8 folders (Box 12)
  - 1947
    - A-W, 17 folders (Box 12)
  - 1948
    - A-W, 23 folders (Box 12)
  - 1949
    - A-M, 10 folders (Box 12)
    - N-Y, 10 folders (Box 13)
  - 1950
    - A-Z, 31 folders (Box 13)
  - 1951
    - B-Z, 22 folders (Box 13)
  - 1952 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - 1953
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - 1954
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Ypsilanti State Hospital (Box 14)
  - 1955
    - A (Box 14)
    - Alexander Group (Box 14)
    - American College of Surgeons (Box 14)
    - B-C, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Chest Club (Box 14)
    - D-G, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Genesee County Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Box 14)
    - H-I, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Insurance (Box 14)
    - J (Box 14)
    - Jackson County Sanatorium (Box 14)
    - K (Box 14)
    - Kimball County Sanatorium (Box 14)
    - L-M, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Michigan Heart Association (Box 14)
    - Michigan State Sanatorium (Box 14)
    - Michigan Tuberculosis Sanatorium Commission (Box 14)
    - Morris, Dr. Joseph (Box 14)
    - Moynahan, Maynard J. (Box 14)
    - National Heart Institute (Box 14)
    - N-P, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Postgraduate, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - R-S, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital (Box 14)
    - T (Box 14)
    - Thoracic Surgery Funds (Box 14)
    - University Hospital (Box 14)
    - V (Box 14)
    - Washtenaw Medical Society (Box 14)
    - Wayne County Medical Society (Box 14)
    - X-ray Reports Unregistered Patients (Box 14)
    - X-Z (Box 14)
  - 1956
    - A (Box 14)
    - Alexander Monograph (Box 14)
    - Alexander Memorial Fund (Box 14)
    - John Alexander Surgical Society (Box 14)
    - American Association for Thoracic Surgery (Box 14)
    - American Cancer Society (Box 14)
    - American College of Surgeons (Box 14)
    - American Heart Association (Box 14)
    - B-C, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Chest Club (Box 14)
    - D (Box 14)
    - Davin Fund (Box 15)
    - E (Box 15)
    - Ethicon, Inc. (Box 15)
    - F-G, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Genesee County Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - H-I, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Instruments (Box 15)
    - Insurance (Box 15)
    - J (Box 15)
    - Jackson County Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - K (Box 15)
    - Kimball Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - L-M, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Medical School (Box 15)
    - Michigan Heart Association (Box 15)
    - Michigan Tuberculosis Sanatorium Commission (Box 15)
    - Michigan State Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - N (Box 15)
    - Operation Room Committee (Box 15)
    - P (Box 15)
    - Postgraduate Inactive File (Box 15)
    - Patients Unregistered (Box 15)
    - R-S, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - T (Box 15)
    - Thoracic Surgery Staff and Funds (Box 15)
    - U (Box 15)
    - University Hospital (Box 15)
    - W-Z, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1957
    - American Association for Thoracic Surgery (Box 15)
    - American Board of Surgery (Box 15)
    - American College of Surgeons (Box 15)
    - American Heart Association (Box 15)
    - American Medical Association (Box 15)
    - American Surgical Association (Box 15)
    - Applications (Box 15)
    - B (Box 15)
    - Board of Thoracic Surgery (Box 15)
    - C (Box 15)
    - Cancer Research (Box 15)
    - Chest Club (Box 15)
    - Codman & Shurtleff (Box 15)
    - D-E, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Ethicon, Inc. (Box 15)
    - F-G, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Genesee County Tuberculosis Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - H-I, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Instruments (Box 15)
    - J (Box 15)
    - Jackson County Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - Junior Lectures (Box 15)
    - K (Box 15)
    - Kimball Sanatorium (Box 15)
    - L-M, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Medical School (Box 16)
    - Michigan Heart Association (Box 16)
    - Michigan Tuberculosis Sanatorium Commission (Box 16)
    - Michigan State Sanatorium, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - N (Box 16)
    - National Heart Institute (Box 16)
    - O (Box 16)
    - Operating Room Committee (Box 16)
    - Outpatient Equipment (Box 16)
    - P (Box 16)
    - Patients Unregistered (Box 16)
    - Postgraduate Inactive File, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Postgraduate Medicine (Box 16)
    - R-S, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Sanatoriums (Box 16)
    - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Society of Thoracic Surgeons of Great Britain and Ireland (Box 16)
    - T (Box 16)
    - Thoracic Surgery Funds (Box 16)
    - U (Box 16)
    - University Hospital, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - V-Y, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - 1958
    - Alexander Society (Box 16)
    - American Heart Association (Box 16)
    - American Trudeau Society (Box 16)
    - B-C, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Chest Club (Box 16)
    - D (Box 16)
    - Dana Fund (Box 16)
    - E-G, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Genesee Memorial Hospital (Box 16)
    - H-J, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Jackson County Sanatorium (Box 16)
    - K (Box 16)
    - Kimball Sanitorium (Box 16)
    - L-M, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Michigan Heart Association (Box 16)
    - Michigan State Sanatorium (Box 16)
    - P (Box 16)
    - Patients Unregistered (Box 16)
    - R (Box 16)
    - Research Fellowships (Box 16)
    - S (Box 16)
    - Surgery Department (Box 16)
    - T-U, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - University Hospital (Box 16)
    - W-Z, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1959
    - Miscellaneous, 1 folders (Box 16)
  - 1960
    - Miscellaneous, 1 folders (Box 16)
- Operative Notes 1927-1954, 2.8 linear feet
  The second series Operative Notes, documents thoracic surgical procedures. The material consists of history sheets for each case, which report patient information, preoperative diagnosis, anesthesia used, the operating doctor, and a brief but detailed description of the procedure. The material is arranged in three parts, consisting of the surgical notes of John Alexander from 1927 to 1954, the notes of Cameron Haight from 1935 to 1952, and a series of notes from 1927 to 1934 which are filed by the type of procedure performed (e.g., thoracoplasty). In most cases the copies of notes filed by procedure are carbon copies of the chronologically arranged notes maintained by Alexander and Haight.
  - Dr. John Alexander
    - 1927 (Box 17)
    - 1928 (Box 17)
    - 1929 (Box 17)
    - 1930 (Box 17)
    - 1931 (Box 17)
    - 1932 (Box 17)
    - 1933, 11 folders (Box 17)
    - 1934, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - 1935, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - 1936 (Box 17)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 17)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 17)
    - 1950 (Box 17)
    - 1951 (Box 17)
    - 1952 (Box 17)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 17)
  - Dr. Cameron Haight
    - 1935 (Box 18)
    - 1936, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 1940 (Box 18)
    - 1941 (Box 18)
    - 1943 (Box 18)
    - 1944 (Box 18)
    - 1945 (Box 18)
    - 1946 (Box 18)
    - 1947 (Box 18)
    - 1948 (Box 18)
    - 1949 (Box 18)
    - 1950 (Box 18)
    - 1951 (Box 18)
    - 1952 (Box 18)
  - Procedural Operative Notes
    - Anterolateral Thoracoplasty, 1927-1934 (Box 19)
    - Broncoscopic Aspiration of Secretions, 1931-1933 (Box 19)
    - Broncoscopic Drainage, 1931-1934 (Box 19)
    - Broncoscopy, 1931-1934, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Cauterization, 1931-1934 (Box 19)
    - Closed Drainage of Empyema, 1928-1934 (Box 19)
    - Division of Adhesions, 1932-1934 (Box 19)
    - Drainage of Abscess, 1927-1934 (Box 19)
    - Empyemic Thoracoplasty, 1927-1934 (Box 19)
    - Extrapleural Thoracoplasty, 1927-1934 (Box 19)
    - Lobectomy, 1928-1934 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous Explorations (Successful & Unsuccessful), 1927-1934 (Box 19)
    - Open Drainage Empyema, 1927-1934, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Pneumonolysis, 1934 (Box 19)
    - Posterolateral Thoracoplasty, 1932-1934 (Box 19)
    - Sinus Operations, 1927, 1934 (Box 19)
    - Thoracoplasty, 1927-1934 (Box 19)
    - Thoracotomy, 1928-1934 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous Operations on Extremities, 1931-1935 (Box 19)
- Papers and Notes 1929-1949, 0.2 linear feet
  The series Papers and Notes contains manuscripts of presentations and published articles, many of which include case studies drawn from the operative notes. Topics include empyema, and the surgical treatment of tuberculosis.
  - "The Empyema Problem," (Alexander), 1929 (Box 19)
  - " Monaldi Drainage" 1947 (Box 19)
  - "Routine Bronchoscopy in TBC," n.d. (Box 19)
  - "The Surgical Management of the Acute Recurring and Chronic Forms of Spontaneous Pneumothorax," (Haight & Alexander), 1947 (Box 19)
  - "Surgical Treatment of Tuberculosis Empyema and its Pyogenic Complications," (Haight), 1941 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous Reprints 1934-1949 (Box 19)
- Photographs and Negatives 1929-1957, 1 linear feet
  The final series Photographs and Negatives, further expands the information contained in the preceding two series. The bulk of the material contains negatives (4 x 5, 5 x 7, and 8 x 10 inch formats) illustrating thoracic patients, procedures, and equipment primarily from 1929 to 1942. Illustrations include negatives of chest X-rays, resected tissues, and post-operative images of patients. Like the Operative Notes series, the negatives are arranged by the type of treatment or procedure. Other material includes photographs and negatives of the Army courses in thoracic surgery taught at the University of Michigan during World War II, and prints of the 1943 junior and senior surgical sections. One print of John Alexander as well as negatives of the thoracic surgery staff is also included here.
  - Negatives of Thoracic Procedures and Patients
    - Abscess (Box 20)
    - Aortectomy (Box 20)
    - Bronchostenosis (Box 20)
    - Bronchiectasis (Box 20)
    - Congenital Atresia of the Esophagus with Tracheoesophageal Fistula (Box 20)
    - Empyema (Tuberculosis and Non-Tuberculosis), 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Esophagus (Box 20)
    - Extrapleural Pneumonolysis (Box 20)
    - Heart (Box 20)
    - Ineffectual Pneumonectomy and Phrenic (Steele Paper) (Box 20)
    - Intrapleural Pneumonolysis, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Intratracheal Suction (Box 20)
    - Lung Abscess (includes prints) (Box 20)
    - Management of Poor Risk Thoracoplasty Patients (Box 20)
    - Mediastinal Physiology and Hernias (Box 20)
    - Mediastural Abscess (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous Negatives (Box 20)
    - Monaldi Drainage and Thoracoplasty (Box 20)
    - Oblique X-rays (prints only) (Box 20)
    - Pectus Excavation (Box 20)
    - Phrenic (Box 20)
    - Pulmonary Resections for Tuberculosis (statistics) (Box 20)
    - Pulmonary Tuberculosis Cavity Drainage (Box 20)
    - Shaw Article (prints only) (Box 20)
    - Subpleuric Abscess (Box 20)
    - Supraperiosteal Pneumonolysis (Box 20)
    - Thoracoplasty Posteriolateral, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Tuberculoma (Box 20)
    - Tuberculosis Bilateral Collapse Therapy (Box 20)
    - Tuberculosis Tracheobronchitis (Box 20)
  - Photographs
    - Army Course (includes negatives), 1943 (Box 20)
    - Junior and Senior Surgical Sections, 1943 (Box 20)
    - Malacca Tuberculosis Unit, circa 1945 (Box 20)
    - Patients
      - 1933-1942, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - 1946-1957 and n.d., 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Staff (includes negatives), circa 1934-1935 (Box 20)